Hello everyone and
welcome to English Pod.
My name is Marco. My
name is Katherine and Marco
I can tell you right
now I'm already hungry
just thinking about
our lesson today. That's
right today we have another food lesson our
world cuisine lesson for today is all about
Mexican food. Okay
Mexican food comes from the
country Mexico but
also parts of the United
States like Texas has
something called Tex-Mex.
So you're going to
hear a lot about these
kinds of foods there.
Let's check out today's dialogue.
Hello sir welcome to Pistolir
restaurant may take you order.
Yes I would like the chicken cheese
and chiladas with a side of guacamole.
Sorry sir but we
ran out of chicken.
May I suggest our delicious beef
burritos or cheese quesadillas?
Both include a side of
guacamole and jalapenos.
Sure I'll have the burrito if you have
nachos. Of course sir our nachos come
with melted cheese and chili. Sounds
good would you like anything to drink?
Sure I'll have a corona.
Alright we're back so a lot of
great dishes from
Mexico let's take a closer
look at some of those
on language takeaway.
Language takeaway. So first up
Marco we have the word enchilada.
That's right we have some chicken
cheese and chiladas so this dish has
chicken and cheese but
enchilada what is that?
Okay so it's basically
a wrap that is covered
in cheese right?
That's right so it has a
base of a flour tortilla
so a tortilla is like
a wrap as you said let's
consider it as flatbread.
Very thin. Very
thin and it rolls
up and it's covered with cheese and inside
it has chicken very very good. That's right
and just a warning you're going to hear me
say the American pronunciation and chilada
and you're going to hear
Marco say a more appropriate.
A little bit with a more
Hispanic accent to it.
That's right so the second
one we've got is guacamole.
Wacamole that's right we
say wakamole and this is
from the avocado fruit.
That's right avocados are
green fruits they have
a skin so you take the
skin off and you usually make
guacamole with other ingredients.
Right it has a
little bit of lemon,
onion, tomato, maybe a
little spicy. Really good stuff.
So yeah it comes from that fruit that you
said and it's kind of like a paste right?
It's yeah it's something
that we often use as a dip so I
can dip my potato chips
or my tortilla chips in it
or I can use it as a
sauce. All right very good
and our next and probably
one of the most popular
dishes in the Mexican
cuisine world is a beef burrito.
Burrito so a burrito is
another kind of wrap.
We have a tortilla like
you said earlier and
inside there are many
different things so usually
some rice and some beans and
some meat maybe beef or chicken.
That's right so
considerate kind of like
a sandwich more or less but
in a blanket instead of in bread.
Exactly in a blanket
and then also
we have cheese quesadillas.
Now also these are made
from the same
blanket of tortilla.
That's right so this thin
tortilla this flour tortilla is put
on top and on bottom
and inside you have some
cheese some melted
cheese or other times you can
have cheese and chicken
and usually you find it
it's a circle but it's
cut into four pieces so
it looks like a pieces
of a pie. That's right and
actually what you do is
you heat it up in a pan
so the cheese inside melts
and it's very very delicious.
It is and sometimes
you have this with
a side of jalapeno. Okay
this is a some type of
vegetable I would
guess. It's a pepper.
It's a pepper. Right so this is
a very very spicy pepper that
people often use to
make things taste hot.
That's right so you can see
them they're usually green
and they're very very
spicy so if you bite into
it it'll burn your mouth.
It will and sometimes
people like to put
these on our next dish.
What's the next dish Marco?
We have some nachos.
Okay this is a classic
Tex-Mex dish like I was
saying so a lot of
Americans love to eat this
and nachos are basically
a plate of tortilla chips
with what on top? Usually
it has melted cheese
and maybe some chili
like we see in the dialogue
so it will kind of just
consider a plate full of
these chips kind of they
look like potato chips
but they're made out of
flour and on top a lot of
cheese and maybe some
meat or some chili on top.
And Americans also like
to put sour cream on top.
Oh yes sour cream is
very popular on this dish.
So a lot of dishes these are
probably the most popular
ones that you can find at
most Mexican restaurants
and also in Tex-Mex
style cuisine.
So why don't we take
another look at everything and
we'll be back in a bit
with fluency builder.
Hello sir welcome to Pistolera
restaurant may take you order.
Yes I would like the chicken cheese
on chiladas with a side of guacamole.
Sorry sir but we
ran out of chicken.
May I suggest our delicious beef
burritos or cheese quesadillas?
Both include a side of
guacamole and jalapenos.
Sure I'll have the burrito.
Do you have nachos? Of course
sir our nachos come with melted
cheese and chili. Sounds
good would you like
anything to drink?
Sure I'll have a corona.
Alright so Marko today we have only three
things to talk about influencing builder.
The first one is
something that the
waiter said to the
customer. It was to run out of.
That's right he wanted
some chicken cheese and
chiladas but unfortunately
they ran out of chicken.
So the phrasal verb
here is to run out of.
That's right and we heard
the past tense. So unfortunately
we ran out of chicken
this means that we no
longer have chicken.
We sold all of the chicken.
That's right. So for
example if you're in your
car and all of a sudden
you run out of gasoline.
It means your car
will stop running.
That's very bad situation. So to run
out of means to not have anymore.
That's right so you
ran out of money.
Maybe you have no more
money. Another bad situation.
Alright so instead he
ordered a burrito that
included a side of
guacamole and jalapenos.
Okay so the reason we
included this is because
it's important to remember
this as a phrase, a side of.
That's right. So
this burrito comes
with a side of guacamole or
this burrito has a side of beans.
So a side of means a
small portion, a little bit.
That's right. The
most important part
of a side of is that it
doesn't come in the dish
or inside the burrito.
Let's say it just comes
separately on a separate
little plate or it can
come next to yeah
next to the main dish.
So if the main dish is tacos,
you can say I want tacos
with a side of black
beans. You would get the
black beans in a little
bowl next to you but
that's not the main
thing. Exactly, exactly.
So a side of. Now for our
last phrase when we talked
about the nachos they came
with melted cheese and chili.
So what do we mean
by they come with melted
cheese and chili? Okay
so this verb to come with
means that they they
have as a part of the dish.
So this is not a side.
Right. Not like before
when we were talking
about a side of this means
that in the case of nachos
the nachos have on them
on top cheese and
chili. That's right.
So sometimes if you go to
McDonald's and you buy a meal,
you get a burger and
the burger comes with
french fries and a Coke
included in the meal.
Or you can say unfortunately
this meal does not
come with a drink. So you
have to order the drink extra.
That's right. Okay.
So a lot of great stuff.
Let's take another look
and we'll be right back.
Hello sir. Welcome
to pistol air restaurant.
May I take your order?
Yes, I would like the chicken
cheese and chiladas
with a side of guacamole.
Sorry sir but we ran out
of chicken. May I suggest
our delicious beef burritos
or cheese quesadillas?
Both include a side of
guacamole and jalapenos.
Sure I'll have the burrito.
Do you have nachos?
Of course sir. Our nachos come
with melted cheese and chili.
Sounds good. Would you like
anything to drink? Sure I'll have a corona.
Alright so Mexican food.
Very very delicious and
as we see it has a lot of
cheese and most dishes.
It does a lot of cheese
and also a lot of tortillas.
So tortillas are
these usually round
flat pancake-like
things. They're not sweet.
They're savory and I usually
put things in them like
tacos or fajillas or
burritos. That's right.
And there's two kinds
right? That's right.
So you have tortillas that
are made from flour that are
usually white and then
you have corn tortillas that
are made from corn
and they're usually a little
bit more yellow. That's
right. So it's actually
Mexican food is very
very good but usually it's
a little bit spicy so if
you don't really like
a spicy food you should
tell the waiter or waitress
to not make it
spicy. That's right.
If you don't eat spicy food
you certainly don't want to eat
any jalapeno
peppers. That's right.
I'm actually not really
a fan of spicy food.
So for example I really
cannot eat jalapeno peppers.
See I'm the opposite. I
love spicy food so I often
order green enchiladas which
have a spicy jalapeno green sauce.
Yeah they're very very spicy.
So this is part of our
mini series that we have all
about world foods. We've
already taken a look at Italian food.
We have Mexican
food. Next we'll be
looking at Indian food
Korean food a lot of great
international foods
coming up. Yummy.
So let us know do you like
Mexican food? Have you ever had
Mexican food and if we
left off some kind of Mexican
food like tacos let
us know. That's right.
Our website is EnglishPod.com
we'll see you there.
All right bye.